Register to The Harold Rome Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Harold Rome Papers
1873-1988
MSS 49
Yale University Music Library
46
(97 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, photographs, art works, and additional materials by and about the American musical theater composer Harold Rome (1908-1993)
Rome, Harold, 1908-1993
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Harold Rome Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Harold Rome in 1984.
Arrangement
In 9 series as follows: I. Music by Rome. II. Scripts and Lyrics. III. Production Materials, Contracts, Royalty Statements, and Related Correspondence. IV. Correspondence. V. Programs. VI. Art Works, Exhibit Catalogues, and Inventories. VII. Clippings. VIII. Photographs. IX. Miscellaneous Items. X. Sound Recordings.
Scope and Contents
The Harold Rome Papers include holograph, manuscript, and published musical works by Rome. These include vocal music, piano works, and a string quartet as well as the stage works. Among the stage works are some that have never been produced. Also included are scripts and lyrics, many of them in Rome's hand. There are production materials which include contracts, royalty statements, and related correspondence. The correspondence, mostly from others, includes letters from many illustrious friends and collaborators. There are numerous photographs of Rome and his stage and art works, including many slides and negatives. Twelve scrapbooks containing programs, correspondence, clippings and photographs, have been disassembled and the items assigned to the appropriate series. The clippings have been copied onto acid-free paper and the originals discarded.
The Papers also contain original art works by Harold Rome. An inventory of 75 oil paintings and watercolors appears in this register. Approximately 128 cassette and reel-to-reel tapes and 158 sound discs (40 45s, 83 78s, and 35 LPs) were transferred to Yale's Historical Sound Recordings collection.
A song index was compiled to indicate the shows in which songs appeared. The index also includes cross-references of variant titles for a show. Cross-references also appear within the register and in the series introductions. The song index was compiled for the general convenience of researchers. It is important to note, however, that not all of the songs listed there are present in the Harold Rome Papers.
Boxes and folders are numbered consecutively, except for oversized boxes and folders, which are housed at the end.
The Papers were a gift of Harold Rome. They came to the Library in three installments: seventeen boxes of music in September, 1984; manuscripts, paintings, correspondence, agreements and contracts, programs, and sound recordings, on July 19, 1986; and seventeen boxes of additional manuscripts, scripts, and sound recordings in February, 1988.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Jacob ("Hecky") Rome was born in Hartford, Connecticut, on May 27, 1908. His education included a B.A. from Yale College (1929), studies at the Yale Law School (1929-1930), a B.F.A. from the Yale School of Architecture (1934), and courses at the Yale Schools of Art and Music. He played piano in the Yale orchestra, making four trips to Europe with the group, and supported himself by playing with dance bands and for dance classes. This period also saw the birth of Rome's interest in African art, a fascination sparked when Rome visited Paris in 1930 and attended an exhibition of African sculpture there.
In 1934 Rome headed to New York to begin a career in architecture. What began as supplemental music jobs, however, blossomed into a more fulfilling and lucrative profession than architecture. During his three seasons (1935-1937) at Green Mansions (a summer resort in the Adirondacks), he produced musicals, wrote songs, and played the piano. His genius for songwriting was evident, and it was not long before his songs were sung by Gypsy Rose Lee and the Ritz Brothers.
In 1937, Louis Schaeffer hired Rome to write songs and be the rehearsal pianist for the revue Pins and Needles, which was produced and performed by I.G.L.W. union members. When, in 1937, the show opened in New York, it met with such wide acclaim that it moved on to Broadway and ran there and on the road for four years, establishing Rome as a composer and lyricist. He won an ASCAP award for the song "Sunday in the Park" from Pins and Needles, followed by another for the song "Franklin D. Roosevelt Jones" from the 1938 revue Sing Out the News (produced by Max Gordon, with sketches by George S. Kaufman and Moss Hart, and songs by Harold Rome).
There followed revues, mostly sociopolitical, including Sing for Your Supper (1939); Streets of Paris (1939); and The Little Dog Laughed (1940), a musical based on the book by Joseph Schrank. Lunchtime Follies (1942), to which Rome contributed several songs, was a series of forty-five minute morale-boosting revues presented to workers at war-materiel factories. It included sketches by George S. Kaufman, Moss Hart, and Maxwell Anderson, and was produced and supervised by Kurt Weill. This was followed by Star and Garter (1942) and Let Freedom Sing (1942).
As a serviceman during World War II, Rome wrote songs for the army shows Stars and Gripes (1943) and Skirts (1944), the latter done in collaboration with fellow PFC Frank Loesser. Rome's return to civilian life was the theme for his next revue, Call Me Mister (1946), performed by former servicemen and servicewomen, among others.
That's the Ticket (1948), a musical based on a book by Julius and Philip G. Epstein, was directed by Jerome Robbins. This was followed by four more revues: Pretty Penny (1949), with sketches by Jerome Chodorov and directed by George S. Kaufman; Alive and Kicking (1950); Michael Todd's Peep Show (1950); and Bless You All (1950), with sketches by Arnold Auerbach.
Apart from Romanoff and Juliet (1957, play by Peter Ustinov with incidental music by Rome, directed by George S. Kaufman and produced by David Merrick), and La Grosse Valise (1965, for which Rome wrote the lyrics), the final productions were the book-musicals Wish You Were Here (1952, book by Arthur Kober and Joshua Logan, directed by Logan), Fanny (1954, book by S.N. Behrman and Joshua Logan based upon the trilogy by Marcel Pagnol, directed by Logan and produced by Logan and David Merrick), Destry Rides Again (1959, book by Leonard Gershe, produced by Merrick), I Can Get It for You Wholesale (1962, book by Jerome Weidman, produced by Merrick), The Zulu and the Zayda (1965), and Gone With the Wind, which opened in Tokyo as Scarlett (1970), went on to London (1972), and finally moved to Los Angeles (1973) to begin a United States tour.
In his book Show Tunes (1986), Steven Sushin describes Harold Rome's revues as having "sparkling comedy lyrics for everyday characters, set to bright and fresh music," and his musicals as having "rich, emotional scores." This accounts for the tremendous popularity of the shows and individual songs, as well as for their numerous performances and recordings. In fact, many of the shows were vehicles that launched the careers of performers such as Jack Cassidy, Bob Fosse, Betty Garrett, Elliot Gould, Buddy Hackett, Florence Henderson, Carl Reiner, Jerome Robbins, Barbra Streisand, and William Warfield.
Harold Rome died in New York on October 26, 1993.
Arlen, Harold, 1905-1986; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Bennett, Tony, 1926-; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989; Carlisle, Kitty, 1910-2007; Chasins, Abram, 1903-1987; Chevalier, Maurice, 1888-1972; Chodorov, Jerome; Comden, Betty, 1919-2006; Crawford, Joan, 1908-1977; De Mille, Agnes, 1905-1993; Dietz, Howard, 1896-1983; Douglas, Melvyn, 1901-1981; Drake, Alfred, 1914-1992; Engel, Lehman, 1910-1982; Foote, Horton, 1916-2009; Francis, Arlene, 1907-2001; Freeman, Paul, 1936-2015; Furness, Betty, 1916-1994; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983; Goodman, Benny, 1909-1986; Gorme, Eydie, 1928-2013; Grauer, Ben; Green, Adolph, 1914-2002; Green, Stanley, 1923-; Hammerstein, Oscar, II, 1895-1960; Hart, Moss, 1904-1961; Herlie, Eileen, 1918-2008; Ionesco, Eugène, 1912-1994; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Kapp, David, 1904-1976; Kazan, Elia, 1909-2003; Kert, Larry, 1930-1991; Kober, Arthur, 1900-1975; Kroll, Lucy; Lane, Burton, 1912-1997; Lawrence, Steve, 1935-; Layton, Joe, 1931-; Leinsdorf, Erich, 1912-1993; Lerner, Alan Jay, 1918-1986; Lieberson, Goddard, 1911-1977; Mercer, Johnny, 1909-1976; Merrick, David, 1911-2000; Novotná, Jarmila, 1907-1994; Osborn, Paul, 1901-1988; Porter, Cole, 1891-1964; Resnik, Regina, 1922-2013; Rigby, Harry; Rittman, Trude, 1908-2005; Robbins, Jerome, 1918-1998; Robbins, Warren M.; Rodgers, Dorothy, 1909-1992; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979; Rome, Harold, 1908-1993; Sardi, Vincent, 1915-2007; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Schubert, Bernard, 1895-1988; Schwartz, Arthur, 1900-1984; Segáll, Bernardo; Silber, Irwin, 1925-2010; Vacha, John; Weidman, Jerome, 1913-1998; Wood, Audrey, 1905-; Wouk, Herman, 1915-
- Music by Rome, 1935-1981; Series I; 24.2' (58 boxes)
  General
  This series includes holograph, manuscript, printed, and published music by Rome. The music is divided into four subseries (A-D) by genre, with the last subseries (E) being MUSIC BY OTHERS.
  The musical works are arranged alphabetically within each subseries, except for MUSIC BY OTHERS, which is arranged alphabetically by composer, then by title. Uniform titles are used to bring together all of the manifestations of a work with different titles. Cross references between parts of a work, various forms of a title, and pieces which are included with another work appear in the index.
  Many lyrics remain interspersed among musical sketches so as not to harm any original order helpful to researchers. Cross-references have therefore been made from SCRIPTS AND LYRICS.
  Scripts and lyrics on legal sheets have been copied onto acid-free paper, and the originals discarded.
  Boxes and folders are numbered consecutively throughout the entire series, with the exception of three oversized boxes housed at the end of the collection (boxes 93, 94, and 95).
  - Stage Works, I.A
    - [Alive and kicking. Cry baby. Vocal score] Cry Baby! / Harold Rome., 1 manuscript vocal score (4 p.); 32 cm. (Box 01, Folder 01)
      Holograph, signed, in pencil
    - [Author, Author. Don't go away. Vocal score] Don't Go Away / Harold Rome. -- 1960 Mar. 4., 1 manuscript vocal score ([2] p.); 31 cm. (Box 01, Folder 02)
    - [Author, Author. I love a musical. Vocal score] I Love A Musical / Harold Rome., 1 manuscript vocal score ([2] p.); 35 cm. (Box 01, Folder 02)
      Holograph, signed, in pencil and ink
    - [Bless you all], 1949-1950; 1 manuscript condensed score (226 p. in various pagings) + 19 parts; 32 cm. (Box 01-04, Folder 3-23)
      Manuscript in ink (in part, photocopies) and holograph in pencil with markings
      Score contains some musical numbers with piano accompaniment only
      Contents [in the order in which they were found]: Rose ballet. 18 Love that man - fanfares. 1 Overture. 2 Bless you all. 2A Do you know a better way to make a living? 3 Truman Capote. 3A Don't want to write about the South. 4 I can hear it now. 4A I can hear it now dance. 5 "Hear" utility. 6 When. 33 Bless utility. 8 Little things (New intro). 9 A rose is a rose. 10 A rose is a rose 1st act ballet / Music by Mischa and Wesley Portnoff. Rose utility. 11 Love letter to Manhattan. 20 Entr'acte. 21 Summer dresses - intro. 22 Summer dresses. 23 Summer dresses - utility. 24 Take off the coat. 44 Summer dresses - utility. 27 Rose utility. 28 You never know what hit you. 29 Hit you - encore. 30 Thirty years ago. 32 Finale ultimo. 33 Weekend finale. 25 New Painting intro. 25A The painting song. 31 Thirty years ago encore.
    - [Bless you all] Bless You All., 1 manuscript score (ca. [665] p.) in various pagings; 32-43 cm. (Box 93–94)
      Holograph in pencil and ink, in part manuscript (photocopy)
      Music and lyrics by Harold Rome
      Contents: 2. Bless you all (condensed score, copy laid in). 3. I can hear it now. 5. Those little things. 10. Weekend. 10A. Weekend Finale. 12. A rose is a rose. 15. Love letter to Manhattan. Television crossover. 17. Love that man. 19. Little white house. 20. Heaven commercial. 20A. Home sweet home. 21. Voting blues. 22. Love that man. 25. Finale Act I. Introduction to overture. Summer dresses (Overture). 27. Summer dresses. Summer dresses insert. Take off the coat. Coat utility. 31. Take off the coat [different orchestration]. 36. The painting song. 38. Introduction to Southland (Truman Capote). 39. Southland. 41. Desert flame. Change Desert flame. 43. Be a folksinger. 45. Finale ultimo
      Score incomplete, miscellaneous inserts and utility music at end
      Lyrics not included
    - [Bless you all. Bless utility] Bless utility., 1 manuscript vocal score (2 p.) + 20 parts; 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 24)
      Manuscript (photocopies)
    - [Bless you all. Desert flame] 26: The desert flame., 1 manuscript condensed score (33 p.); 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 25)
      Manuscript (photocopy) with markings and additions in pencil Labeled "conductor"
    - [Bless you all. Heaven commercial (Sketches)] Heaven Commercial: (Love that man)., [2] p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 26)
      Holograph in pencil
      Note: Barry: - Jos Gabriel Blow
      Sheet laid in with notes in ink
    - [Bless you all. Love that man] Love that man. -- 1950., 1 manuscript vocal score (11 p.) + 23 manuscript parts; 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 27-28)
      Manuscript in ink (in part, photocopies)
      Vocal score with orchestral cues
      Includes multiple copies of parts
      Note on envelope containing vocal parts: Kenneth Smith / 325 W. 45th / Bless You All / Hellinger Theatre
    - [Bless you all. Rose is a rose finale. Chorus score] "Bless You All": Rose is a rose - finale., 1 manuscript chorus score (4 p.); 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 29)
      Manuscript (photocopy) with pencil additions
      Ten copies, with singers' names on each score
    - [Bless you all. Rose is a rose. Vocal score] A rose is a rose: 1st act ballet / Music by Mischa and Wesley Portnoff., 1 manuscript vocal score (13 p.) + 19 parts; 32 cm. (Box 05, Folder 30)
      Manuscript in ink (in part, photocopies) with pencil markings
      Note on folder: Finished - ready to play M.P.; old Rose Ballet
    - [Bless you all. Rose is a rose; arr.] A rose is a rose: Fox Trot: From the New Musical "Bless You All" / Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome; Dance Orch. Arrangement by Jack Mason. New York: Crawford Music Corporation, c1950., 15 parts; 27 cm. (Box 05, Folder 31)
    - [Bless you all. Selections], ca. 1948-1950; ca. 400 parts; 32 cm. (Box 05-07, Folder 32-53)
      Manuscript in ink with pencil additions (in part, photocopies)
      These parts were found grouped by musical number, and every part within a musical number was counted
      Includes published parts for "Two Guitars" (Harry Horlick; arr. by Louis Katzman. -- New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., [c1925]. Pl. No.: 23760-22)
    - [Bless you all. Selections], ca. 1949; 20 parts; 32 cm. (Box 07-09, Folder 54-65)
      Manuscript in ink (in part, photocopies) with pencil additions
      Published parts for "Two Guitars" laid in
    - [Bless you all. Selections], ca. 1948; 11 manuscript parts; 32 cm. (Box 09, Folder 66)
      Manuscript (photocopies) with pencil additions
      Vocal and choral parts
      Duplicates (32) with markings and performers' names laid in
      Includes vocal and chorus scores
    - [Bless you all. Selections], 1949; 1 manuscript part; 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 67)
      Trumpet 1 and 2 part in a folder labeled "Out music"
    - [Bless you all. Selections. Vocal score] Bless You All / Harold Rome. -- 1948-1950., 1 manuscript vocal score ([70] p.) in various pagings; 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 68)
      Holograph signed, in pencil, in part manuscript in ink
      Typescript lyrics to five songs laid in
      Note on envelope: Original manuscripts BLESS YOU ALL 1949-1950
      Contents [in the order in which they were found]: New verse for a rose is a rose. The painting song. I can hear it now. Take off the coat. Take off the coat (verse). A rose is a rose (verse). Bless you all (Opening). Summer dresses. Just a little white house. Love letter to Manhattan. Love that man. Weekend. Don't want to write about the south. Be a folk singer. Voting blues. I can hear it now. Those little things (meant so much to me). The shifty fifties
    - [Bless you all. Selections. Vocal score], 1948; 1 manuscript vocal score (34 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 69)
      Manuscript (photocopy) with pencil markings
      Sheet with pencil additions and a note laid in
    - [Bless you all. Take off the coat; arr.] Take off the coat: Slow Fox Trot: From the New Musical "Bless You All" / Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome; Dance Orch. Arrangement by Jack Mason. New York: Crawford Music Corporation, c1951., 16 parts; 27 cm. (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - [Bless you all. 20's strike back] The 20's strike back: (Thirty years ago) / Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome., 6 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - [Bless you all. Vocal score] Bless you all / Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome., 1 manuscript vocal score ([100] p.) in various pagings; 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 72-73)
      Manuscript (photocopy) with pencil additions, in part holograph in pencil
      The name "Hecht" appears on most numbers
      Contents (in the order in which they were found): Bless you all (Opening). Those little things (meant so much to me). Weekend. Loveletter to Manhattan. Love that man. Just a little white house. Finale III: "Somewhere up there" Heaven commercial. Voting blues: Finale IV. The painting song. Summer dresses. Don't want to write about the South. Act II Ballet: Desert flame / Music by Mischa and Wesley Portnoff. Be a folksinger (2 other copies laid in, one with corrections, the other stamped "Lehman Engel")
      Extra copies of songs from an envelope labeled "Lead Sheets" laid in
    - [Caleb Catlum], 1941 Aug; [57] p. of music; 33 cm. (Box 10, Folder 74)
      Holographs in pencil and ink, in part signed
      Contents: Caleb Catlum's America Act I Scene I. Caleb Catlum's America Scene I Opening. This is just the beginning. Finale. 15. Gimmick song. 1. Welcome to America. 2. Catlum song. Silas Slick. -- 1941 Aug. 4. Fountain of Youth. 5. Wild horses. British are coming. 7. There comes a time. Shivaree. 8. Wedding. 12. Blue + Gray. Campaign song. 13. Sunday go-to-meeting
      Three sheets of script (typescript with pencil notes) laid in
    - [Call me Mister. Drugstore song] #41 Drugstore song. -- 1945-1946., 1 manuscript score ([13] p.); 39 cm. (Box 10, Folder 75)
      Holograph in ink with pencil additions
      Note on envelope: Original manuscript "Call Me Mister" 1945-46
      Portion of the bottom of the score cut off
    - [Call me Mister. Face on the dime. Vocal score] The Face on the Dime: from the Musical Revue "CALL ME MISTER" / Words and Music by Harold Rome. -- N.Y.: M. Witmark & Sons, N.Y., c1946., 1 vocal score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 10, Folder 76)
      Pl. no.: 1812-4
    - [Call me Mister. Military life (Sketches)], [1] sheet of music; 32 cm. (Box 10, Folder 76)
      Holograph in ink
      Note on discarded folder: Military life lead sheet fragment
    - [Call me Mister. Selections. Vocal score] Call Me Mister. -- 1945-1946., 1 manuscript vocal score (76 p.) in various pagings; 33 cm. (Box 10, Folder 77)
      Holograph in pencil, in part signed, and manuscript (photocopy)
      Contents: Going home train. -- c1946 (stamped: Filed Aug 22 1949). Senator's song. Finale. 11. Home again! Finale (discarded). Function (sketch, discarded). Doing the new civilian (discarded -- lyrics ([2] sheets, typescript) laid in). Opening to "Call Me Mister" (adapted from Jodie Chant). 2. Along with me. 8. Call me Mister. 1. Going home train. 14. His old man. 4. Home of our own. 3. Little surplus me. 5. Love remains the same. 10. When we meet again. 7. Military life. 12. Red Ball Express. 15. Senator's song
      Vocal part to "Yuletide, Park Ave" laid in (manuscript in ink with pencil additions)
    - [Call me Mister. South America, take it away; arr.] South America, take it away: From the Musical Revue "Call Me Mister" / Words and music by Harold Rome; Arranged by Johnny Warrington. -- N.Y.: M. Witmark & Sons, c1946., 15 parts; 27 cm. (Box 10, Folder 78)
      Arranged for saxophone 1-5 (E-flat alto saxophone, B-flat tenor saxophone, E-flat baritone saxophone), trumpet 1-3, trombone 1-3, piano, guitar, violin, and double bass
    - [Call me Mister. South America, take it away; arr.] South America, take it away: From the Musical Revue "CALL ME MISTER" / By Harold Rome; Arranged by John J. Morrissey. -- N.Y.: M. Witmark & Sons, N.Y., c1946., 34 parts; 28 cm. (Box 10, Folder 78)
      Arranged for: C piccolo, D-flat piccolo, flute, E-flat clarinet, B-flat clarinet 1-3, alto clarinet, bass clarinet, E-flat alto saxophone 1-2, tenor saxophone, baritone saxophone, oboe, bassoon, F horn 1-4, E-flat horn 1-4, B-flat cornet (conductor) 1-2, B-flat trumpet 1-2, baritone 1-2, trombone 1-2, tuba, and drums
    - [Call me Mister. When we meet again; arr.] When we meet again: From the Musical Revue "Call Me Mister" / Words and Music by Harold Rome; Radiorchestration by Ken Machomber. -- N.Y.: M. Witmark & Sons, c 1946., 17 parts; 27 cm. (Box 10, Folder 78)
      Arranged for saxophone 1-3 (B-flat clarinet), saxophone 4 (bass clarinet), B-flat trumpet 1-2, trombone 1-2, drums, piano, guitar, violin A-C, viola, violoncello, and double bass
    - [Destry rides again. Fair warning; arr.] Fair warning: fox-trot: From the New Musical "Destry Rides Again" / Words and Music by Harold Rome; a masterscore arrangement dance and vocal background arr. by Johnny Warrington. -- New York: Chappell & Co., c1959., 35 parts; 27 cm. (Box 11, Folder 79)
      Arranged for 1st E-flat alto saxophone (3), 2nd B-flat tenor saxophone(3), 3rd E-flat alto saxophone(3), 4th B-flat tenor saxophone(3), 5th B-flat baritone saxophone(3), 1st B-flat trumpet (3), 2nd B-flat trumpet (2), 3rd B-flat trumpet (3), 1st trombone (3), 2nd trombone (2), 3rd trombone (2), drums (2), piano (2), vocal, guitar (2), violin-conductor (2), violin (2), and double bass (2)
      Includes parts arranged for both male (F) and female (D) vocals
    - [Destry rides again. I say hello; arr.] I say hello: fox-trot: From the New Musical "Destry Rides Again" / Words and Music by Harold Rome; a masterscore arrangement dance and vocal background arr. by Johnny Warrington. -- New York: Chappell & Co., Inc., c1959., 31 parts; 27 cm. (Box 11, Folder 80)
      Arranged for 1st E-flat alto saxophone (2), 2nd B-flat tenor saxophone (2), 3rd E-flat alto saxophone (2), 4th B-flat tenor saxophone (2), 5th E-flat baritone saxophone (2), B-flat trumpet 1-3 (6). trombone 1-3 (6), drums (2), vocal (2), piano (2), guitar (2), violin (2), violin-conductor (2), and double bass (2)
      Includes parts arranged for both male (B-flat) and female (G) vocals
    - [Destry rides again. Once knew a fella; arr.] Once knew a fella: fox-trot: From the New, 35 parts; 27 cm. (Box 11, Folder 81)
      Musical "Destry Rides Again" / Words and Music by Harold Rome: a masterscore arrangement dance and vocal background arr. by Johnny Warrington. -- New York: Chappell & Co., Inc., c1959.